Finding Aid for Fred E. Benz motion picture collection, 1929-1950
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Fred E. Benz motion picture collection 1929-1950
Benz, Fred E., d. 1963.
62 reels (in 5 boxes)
93291 Aa 2
Amateur photographer; sixty-two reels of film shot by Benz on various trips.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The films were received as part of the University of Michigan Media Resources Center Collection (Donor no. 4408 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
In 1911, Fred Benz, an Ann Arbor, Michigan native, joined his brothers Victor and Albert in their agricultural implements and feed business called Benz Brothers. Throughout the teens, the brothers expanded their interests into the area of automotive accessories, and in the early twenties opened a Chevrolet dealership. Fred retained an interest in the business but relinquished the operation of Benz Brothers to Albert and became the treasurer of the Ann Arbor Finance Company in 1928. In 1931, he left that position and became vice-president and secretary of The National Company of Ann Arbor. He retired in 1932 but retained his interest in the Benz Brothers operation. Very little additional information exists relating to Benz. He married in 1916 to a woman named Margaret and the marriage lasted until his death in 1963. Benz probably had an interest and skill in photography judging by the quality of the images and the ability with the camera displayed on the rolls of film in this collection.
When the University of Michigan Media Resources Collection was accessioned by the Bentley Historical Library, a number of films were discovered in the vault that were not related to that collection. Within that material were travel films shot by Fred E. Benz. These films, covering the period 1929 to 1950, allow the viewer to experience the sights of the world and its people at those moments in time. The films had been edited together and were probably used by Benz for presentation to local groups and as home entertainment.
The Fred E. Benz Collection contains sixty-two, 400 foot reels of silent 16mm film. It is made up of eight series, one for each trip taken. The series are: Africa, Australia/New Zealand, Guatemala, Havana, Mexico, Russia, South America, and a World Cruise. The contents of each reel are described in the finding aid. Benz has included handwritten descriptions of the images found on the Russian and World Cruise series attached to the inside lids of each can of film. Benz was careful to document most of the locations with a handwritten note displayed before the camera. When cities or natural markers are noted in the finding aid, the identifying information was taken from that supplied by the film maker on the screen or from his notes in the can lids. The spelling of geographic locations in the finding aid reflect the information on the film and not current spellings.
Short notes found with the Mexican footage indicate it was the result of two different trips. The reels retain their original numbering because the numbered reels (1,2,3,4) appear to comprise one trip and numbered/lettered reels (1a, 3a, 4a) comprise the second trip.
The value of the collection is that it captures moments in time, documenting lifestyles, architecture and modes of travel which no longer exist or have evolved over time. Footage exists of London on the eve of war and Shanghai one year before being destroyed by the Japanese invasion.
Perhaps the greater value lies in the depiction of the indigenous lifestyles captured on film. Benz, as an amateur photographer, was interested in the common events that he experienced as he traveled. He captured human life as it went on around him. The collection features extensive footage of people working or playing and children of different cultures going about their daily activities. The films show barren huts in remote areas of Russia in the 1930s, families living under stone bridges outside of Buenos Aires, life-saving competitions in Sydney and the plethora of street markets found in most cultures and countries that he traveled through.
Because these are travel films, the scope of the footage included often extends beyond the geographic area used to identify the series. For example, the Australia footage includes material filmed on various Pacific islands, the Asian continent and Japan. The Russian trip contains footage of England and Northern Europe, and the South American films contain shots of the departure from New York. Each series should be examined for additional geographic content.
Special attention should be given to the Mexican series containing footage of Mt. Rushmore with construction only partially complete. Included as well are extensive shots of bullfighting in addition to other Mexican scenes. Also of note is the extensive depiction of women throughout all of the series. On the canister containing reel 5 in the Russia series is a receipt from United States Navy Department stating that this reel was being forwarded to Chicago for study of the shots of Kirkenes, Norway.
The color in the Africa, Guatemala, Havana, Mexico and South America series is excellent. The wide, clean, lush cityscapes of Havana and Capetown are richly captured in color and give an indication why they were popular travel destinations at this time.
In addition to the eight travel series, the collection also included one reel of World War II footage assembled by Castle Films from public domain footage. This type of film was sold through camera stores and mail order houses and Benz probably purchased a reel for his own use. The identifying writing on the film can is in Benz's handwriting and clearly belonged with his collection.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Africa.; Animals.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Southeast Asia.; Australia.; Brazil.; Bullfighting.; California.; Cemeteries.; Children.; China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; Church architecture.; Country life.; Cuba.; Denmark.; England.; Finland.; Guatemala.; Hawaii.; Indigenous peoples.; Japan.; Lifesaving.; Markets.; Mexico.; Mount Rushmore National Memorial (S.D.); Netherlands.; New Zealand.; Norway.; Oceania.; Peasants.; Poland.; Puerto Rico.; Pygmies.; Rites and ceremonies.; San Francisco Bay Area (Calif.); Soviet Union.; Sweden.; Transportation.; Travel.; Waterfalls.; Women.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Soviet Union.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.
- Africa 1939, 9 reels color
  - Reel 1 - Africa, 400 feet (Box 1)
    [Mombasa (street scenes, stone cutting, native section); Nairobi (street scenes); Namonga River Camp; mirage; Gethins Rhino Camp.]
  - Reel 2 - Africa, 400 feet (Box 1)
    Animals (rhino, zebra, elephants, etc.); Moshi (street market, natives); Mount Kilimanjaro.)]
  - Reel 3 - Africa, 350 feet (Box 1)
    [Animals (lions, lions eating zebra, wildebeest, secretary bird); Safari Camp.]
  - Reel 4 - Africa, 420 feet (Box 1)
    [Animals (hippo, ostrich); Makuru: Kampala: native villages; children; native dress.]
  - Reel 5 - Africa, 400 feet (Box 1)
    [Lake Kivel; volcano with hardened lava; pygmies (chief, family, dances); animals (hippo).]
  - Reel 6 - Africa, 400 feet (Box 1)
    [Velt; Murcherson Falls; the Nile River; Mwanza (children play soccer, cemetery, natives carry heavy loads); animals (crocodiles and eggs, hippo, giant ant hills).]
  - Reel 7 - Africa, 350 feet (Box 1)
    [Africa-Kigoma; Ujiji; Stanley monument; Albertville; women in chains; women washing clothes in stream; native homes; native musicians; Elizabethville; Victoria Falls; Cecil Rhodes' grave.]
  - Reel 8 - Africa, 350 feet (Box 1)
    [Capetown (pan of city, flower market, German embassy, houses, churches, street scene); Lobito (natives cooking, selling hides).]
  - Reel 9 - Africa, 400 feet (Box 1)
    [Las Palmas (street scenes, houses and buildings, penguins being shipped, military band on parade).]
- Australia and New Zealand 1936, 12 reels; black and white and color
  - Reel 1, 400 feet (Box 1)
    Shipboard; Hawaii; Fiji (Suva) (rice planting, native huts); Aukland.
  - Reel 2, 231 feet (Box 1)
    New Zealand (steam spouts, native villages, caves).
  - Reel 3, 225 feet (Box 1)
    [Wellington (street scenes, Wellington monument, buildings); Sydney (street scenes, Peters Ice Cream Co., horse racing track and stables, Jenolan Caves, life-saving and rescue competition, Charles Farrell (actor).]
  - Reel 4, 400 feet (Box 2)
    [Thursday Island (native villages, native body markings); Java (women washing clothes in stream, men bathing, village life, rice planting).]
  - Reel 5, 400 feet (Box 2)
    Jakarta (street scenes, street market, children at play); Singapore (street scenes, post office, monkeys); Bangkok (street scenes, native performers, temples).]
  - Reel 6, 300 feet (Box 2)
    [Brisbane, Australia (pan of city and countryside); animals (snakes, kangaroos, Koala bears); boomerang thrower; native huts.]
  - Reel 7, 427 feet (Box 2)
    [Bali (natives grinding grain, farming, children playing, temples and ruins, native dances).]
  - Reel 8, 423 feet (Box 2)
    [Hong Kong (harbor, street scenes, buildings, natives fishing); Canton (harbor and junks, street scenes).]
  - Reel 9, 430 feet (Box 2)
    [Shanghai (harbor, street scenes); Peiping (street scenes, camels, cars and bikes); The Great Wall.]
  - Reel 10, 393 feet (Box 2)
    [Beppu (Japan) (street scenes, tea garden, hot springs); Kobe; Kyoto (gardens, street scenes, children playing); Nara (street scenes, deer herds in park); Tokyo (street scenes, family picnic).]
  - Reel 11, 200 feet (Box 2)
    [Tokyo (street scenes, hot springs, native dances); Yokahama (street scenes); Hawaii; Hilo (waterfalls).]
  - Reel 12, 140 feet (Box 2)
    Hilo (hilo crater, long shot of city); shipboard to US; long shot of Golden Gate Bridge.
- Guatemala 1950, 4 reels color
  - Reel 1, 375 feet (Box 2)
    [Aerial shots of Guatemala; Guatemala City (street scenes, parks, churches, buildings); rural scenes (making brick and tile, washing clothes in stream, men carry pots on their back); Atitla (houses, gardens, native dress).]
  - Reel 2, 425 feet (Box 2)
    [Villages (street scenes, women washing clothes and self in stream); Santiago (street market, church, weaving, thatching a roof); Quetzltenaorgo (sweeping pan of city, street scenes, carrying water, street market, church); farms; Huemuetenanca (city square, Mayan ruins)]
  - Reel 3, 420 feet (Box 2)
    [Unnamed village (street scenes, street market, potter making bowls); rural houses; Sacapilas (children playing, village scenes); Chichicastenango (pan of village, church, funeral procession, cemetery, children play basketball, street market, religious ceremony-possibly Easter).]
  - Reel 4, 399 feet (Box 2)
    [Solola (pan of city, street market, women carry produce and turkeys to market); Antiqua (street scenes, park, Easter ceremony, churches, gardens, children playing soccer).]
- Havana, Cuba 1950, 2 reels color
  - Reel 1, 400 feet (Box 3)
    [Pan of city; street scenes; gardens; monuments; street peddlers; cemetery; Sloppy Joe's Bar]
  - Reel 2, 250 feet (Box 3)
    [Monuments; cemetery; Rio Crystal Club; gardens; poor sections of town; sugar cane harvest; pineapple plants; children spinning tops; rural scenes.]
- Mexico undated, 7 reels color
  - Reel 1, 250 feet (Box 3)
    [Monterrey (pan across city, street scenes, poor section of town); Saltillo (street scenes, parks, gardens); Xochimilico (canals, flower covered boats, floating market and musicians).]
  - Reel 1a, 340 feet (Box 3)
    [Nuevo Laredo (adobe huts, ropemaking, church, waterfall); Montemoreoos (orange groves, street market, church).]
  - Reel 2, 250 feet (Box 3)
    [Acapulco; Pagoyo (deep sea fishing, street market, pan of village); working in the fields; women wash clothes in canal; native costumes.]
  - Reel 3, 130 feet (Box 3)
    [San Juan (village scenes, land covered with volcanic dust); volcano erupting (very dark and difficult to see).]
  - Reel 3a, 300 feet (Box 3)
    [Paco (street scenes, street market, women washing clothes); Patzcuaro (street market, street performer, natives sewing fishnets); Morelia (street scenes, women washing); scenes of the countryside.]
  - Reel 4, 360 feet (Box 3)
    [Mexico City (street scenes, street market, church, the members of the Equestrian Club, bullfight); Taxco (pan across city, church).]
  - Reel 4a, 450 feet (Box 3)
    [Puebla (street scenes); unidentified sea coast; empty prairie; Mt. Rushmore (working on the figures, scaffolding hanging across faces); Grotlo Geyser; Old Faithful Geyser; Holland, MI (beds of tulips).]
- Russia 1937, 8 reels; black and white and color
  - Reel 1, 340 feet (Box 3)
    [Leaving New York (Statue of Liberty); London (this section alternates between b&w and color stock) (street scenes, newspaper headlines, buildings, changing of the guard); The Hague (milk delivered by wagon, gardens, street scenes); Moneakandam (women wash clothes in stream, native dress).]
  - Reel 2, 340 feet (Box 3)
    [Holland; Berlin (street scenes, zoo, women streetcleaners, Berlin stadium); train trip to Warsaw; Warsaw (street scenes, buildings women pushing carts, funeral).]
  - Reel 3, 294 feet (Box 3)
    [Moscow (Red Square, street scenes); Gorki (street scenes, park, barges along river, a large funeral); rural life along the Volga River.]
  - Reel 4, 309 feet (Box 4)
    [Stalingrad (street scenes, people drawing water at public well); farms; Rostov; Ordjonikidze (street scene, buildings); rural countryside; sheep herders; baby bear cubs; Tiflis (aerial shot of city, street scenes, children playing); Batum (street scenes, people on beach).]
  - Reel 5, 392 feet (Box 4)
    Helsingfors (Finland) (street scenes, buildings, pan across city); Rovaniemi (street scenes, rural scenes); Ivano (Lapland) (carved sleigh, luggage on horse drawn cart, ruins of recent hotel fire); Kirkenes (Norway) (pan of city and bay, street scenes, "City Center", pan of wharf and city from ship).]
  - Reel 6, 440 feet (Box 4)
    [Unidentified fishing village; Hammerfest (Norway) (pans of the harbor, fish market, street scenes); Trondheim (street markets, trains); Bergen (old world architecture, street scenes, street market); men cutting hay; women drying hay.]
  - Reel 7, 344 feet (Box 4)
    Bergen (street scenes); train trip from Bergen to Oslo; Oslow (this section alternates between b&w and color stock) (street scenes, Leiv Eiriksson airplane wreckage, gardens, outdoor restaurant, 20th Century Fox film exchange, buildings, zoo with polar and brown bears, folk costumes, folk dancing).]
  - Reel 8, 155 feet (Box 4)
    [Copenhagen (entire reel alternates between b&w and color) (street scenes, gardens, street vendors, pan across city).]
- South America 1948, 3 reels color
  - Reel 1, 350 feet (Box 4)
    Leaving New York (Statue of Liberty); Ceremonies for crossing the Equator; Rio de Janeiro (Rotary Club of Brazil, pan across the harbor, pan of city, aerial cable car, beaches, race track, street scenes, buildings, zoo with monkeys and tapers); Quitandiula Hotel.]
  - Reel 2, 375 feet (Box 4)
    [Santos (street scenes, zoo, beach, pan of city); San Paulo (snakes); Montevideo (street scenes, buildings); Buenos Aires (street scenes, buildings, street market).]
  - Reel 3, 425 feet (Box 4)
    [Buenos Aires (Street scenes, poor part of town, children at play, cemetery, tombs, funeral, churches, pan of city). Port of Spain (tropical birds and flowers, women and children, native huts, gardens, street scenes, street performers); rural life.]
- World Cruise 1929, 16 reels black and white
  - Reel 1, 300 feet (Box 4)
    [Ship leaves New York; Gibraltar; Algiers (street scenes, native women dancing,); Monaco (pan of city, hills and fields); Nice (pan of city, boardwalk area); Naples; Athens; (Acropolis, Mars Hill, Temple Of Jupiter, Tower of the Winds)]
  - Reel 2, 378 feet (Box 4)
    [Athens (street scenes, women at well); Jerusalem (churches, street scenes, nomads); Dead Sea; camels; pyramids; sphinx.]
  - Reel 3, 330 feet (Box 4)
    [Cairo (zoo); The Nile River; Bombay (zoo, children playing, men bathing in river, street scenes, native dress, railroad station); Delhi.]
  - Reel 4, 409 feet (Box 4)
    [Delhi (German cannons, Taj Mahal, tonga snakes Benares (Holy men covered with ashes); Agra (street market, peasant houses); Kenares (hair cutting, men and women bathing).]
  - Reel 5, 370 feet (Box 5)
    [Calcutta (people mourning the dead, man with leprosy, cobra-mongoose fight, temples, ape smoking, women bathing); Darjeeling (crushing stone for asphalt, women porters).]
  - Reel 6, 341 feet (Box 5)
    [Darjeeling (dancing bear, women carrying water); Madras (street scenes, dog and monkey cart); Madura (street scenes).]
  - Reel 7, 419 feet (Box 5)
    [Colombo (Ceylon) (street scenes, seascapes, native dances); Kandy (elephants working); Sumatra (kick boxing demonstration, native ceremonies, train trip).]
  - Reel 8, 350 feet (Box 5)
    [Buytenzong (Java) (street scenes, harvesting, women washing clothes, steam trains); ceremonies crossing the equator (shipboard ritual).]
  - Reel 9, 351 feet (Box 5)
    [Singapore (native police, street scenes, pineapple market, rubber extraction); Siam; Bangkok (elephants, monkeys, temples, native costumes, native dances, native musicians); Manila (waterfront).]
  - Reel 10, 347 feet (Box 5)
    [Manila (street scenes, cockfight); ricefields; Hong Kong (harbor, pan of city); Canton (street scenes).]
  - Reel 11, 369 feet (Box 5)
    [Hinwangtao (China) (railroad yards); Tangshan (railroad station, local merchants): Peiping (Forbidden City, street scenes, street performers, Summer Palace, Winter Palace, Temple of Heaven, grinding meal) The Great Wall.]
  - Reel 12, 360 feet (Box 5)
    [Peiping (street scenes, water wagon); Beppu (street scenes, native dress, welcoming crowd at train station); Kobe (Japan) (street scenes, street market, woman and child); Kyoto (street scenes, gardens, temples); Nara (street scenes, rickshaws, large heard of deer in city park).]
  - Reel 13, 282 feet (Box 5)
    [Nara (street scenes); Yokohama (street scenes, waterways, drilling a well); Kamakura (street market, people at rail station to see soldiers depart); Nikko (temples, children going to school, Kanaya Hotel); Tokyo (soldiers marching, street scenes, Japanese Boy Scouts).]
  - Reel 14, 209 feet (Box 5)
    [Honolulu (street scenes, passengers debarking the ship, buildings, gardens); Panama Canal; Balboa (statue of Balboa, locks of the canal).]
  - Reel 15, 210 feet (Box 5)
    [Hilo (waterfalls, fern jungle, volcano); shipboard activities and passengers.]
  - Reel 16, 266 feet (Box 5)
    [Stanford University; U.S. Fleet in San Pedro; Long Beach oil wells; Cristabal; Havana (port area, Sloppy Joe's Bar, pan of city from ship); Ann Arbor (train station, downtown pan up First National Bank and Trust Company, Liberty Street facing west (includes Michigan Theater).]
- Non-Benz film, 1 reel black and white
  - Russia Stops Hitler, Castle Films, undated (Box 5)
    [Castle Films, commercial newsreel footage depicting the German invasion of Russia and the eventual counterattack by Soviet troops (1941-1943) from the Russian viewpoint; consists primarily of combat footage]